Michael Hausenblas

Date Of Birth 3rd July 1975

Nationality Austria

Address 32 Bushypark Lawn, Galway, Ireland

Web http://mhausenblas.info/

Email michael.hausenblas@gmail.com



Bio

Michael helps people tap the potential of Big Data by bridging the technical side and the business side. His background is in large-scale data integration research, the Internet of Things, and Web applications and he's experienced in advocacy and standardisation (World Wide Web Consortium, IETF). Michael is sharing his experience with the Lambda Architecture and distributed systems through blog posts and public speaking engagements and is a contributor to Apache Drill.

Prior to MapR, Michael was a Research Fellow at the National University of Ireland, Galway where he acquired research funding totalling over €4M, working with multinational corporations such as Fujitsu, Samsung and Microsoft as well as governmental agencies in Ireland, with up to 15 people reporting to him.

Positions

01/2013 – ongoing	Chief Data Engineer EMEA at MapR Technologies.
11/2010 – 12/2012	Research Fellow and head of DERI's Linked Data Research Centre, National University of Ireland, Galway.
11/2008 – 11/2010	Postdoctoral researcher at the Digital Enterprise Research Institute (DERI), National University of Ireland, Galway.
09/2001 – 11/2008	Researcher in the area of Semantic Web at JOANNEUM RESEARCH Forschungsgesellschaft mbH, Austria.

Professional Activities

2013 - ongoing

- Public speaking engagements at Strata, Hadoop Summit, NoSQL Matters, HUGs, etc.
- Initiating and maintaining advocacy sites such as lambdaarchitecture.net and spark-stack.org
- Providing Hadoop/Big Data on-boarding classes (for example at Gilt)
- Solutions architecting and reviewing
- EMEA-wide pre-sales experience for a Big Data platform
- Writing at InfoQ about Big Data topics

2006 – 2012	 Member of several Working Groups at the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) and co-chairing the RDB2RDF Working Group. Publishing several community standards including RFC7111 at the IETF. 	
2001 – 2012	 Contributed to seven international research projects (EC FP6 and FP7) and served as a project co-ordinator of the Linked Open Data Around-The-Clock Support Action. Published over 50 papers at conferences, workshops and in journals and served on 60+ Programme and Organisation Committees in various conferences and workshops. 	
Education and University Studies		
09/2008	PhD viva voce. Holding a Doctor technicae (Dr. techn.) from the Graz University of Technology, Austria	

Competencies

Doctoral studies at Graz University of Technology, Austria

Software	Pytl
Development	

2004 - 2008

1995 - 2004

04/2004

Python, JavaScript, Java, git, svn, devops basics (shell scripting, Vagrant, etc.)

University studies of Telematics at Graz University of Technology,

Final diploma examination. Holding a Master of Science (MSc.) from the

Repositories:

Austria.

https://github.com/mhausenblas/

http://code.google.com/u/Michael.Hausenblas/

Graz University of Technology, Austria

Tooling

- Hadoop core (HDFS, MapReduce, YARN) and ecosystem components (HBase, Hive, Storm, Drill, etc.),
- Apache Spark stack
- laaS-level cloud computing (Google Compute Engine and AWS)

Soft Skills

- High social competence
- Visionary and creative
- Intercultural alignment
- Good portion of humour